Veteran City Guard of Hartford Collection
Hartford History Center, Hartford Public Library
Veteran City Guard of Hartford Collection
1861-1946
Hartford History Center, Hartford Public Library Hartford, Connecticut
Veteran City Guard of Hartford
20 linear feet
Records, photographs, and artifacts relating to the Veteran City Guard of Hartford
Historical Note
The Hartford City Guard was formed on January 8, 1861. The Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard was organized on November 26, 1867. All past and honorary members of the Hartford City Guard prior to July 5, 1865 were eligible for membership. Members took part in parades, receptions, dinners, and excursions, frequently in association with other semi-military groups. Every year they held a reunion and organized an impressive Memorial Day ceremony. During World War I, they raised a war fund and took part in numerous patriotic activities. At the group’s fiftieth reunion in 1917, they decided not to hold any additional reunions.
Scope and Content
The Veteran City Guard Collection in the Hartford History Center includes scrapbooks, photograph albums, company orders, meeting minutes, ledgers, roll books, record books, reports, and trophies documenting the history of the organization from 1861 to 1916. Records from some years are lacking.
Access Restrictions
The records are stored in a restricted area and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in numbered volumes and four boxes. Documents in Boxes 1 and 2 are filed alphabetically in folders, some according to sender, recipient, or company.
Subject Headings
Corporate Names
Veteran City Guard (Hartford, Conn.); United States. Army; United States. Army--History--Punitive Expedition into Mexico
Subjects
Dinners and dining; Memorial Day; Parades; Portraits; Target practice; Veterans; World War, 1914-1918
Geographic names
Hartford (Conn.)
Genre Terms
Ledgers (Account books); Minutes (Administrative records); Scrapbooks; Photograph albums
Contents:
- Volumes
  - Scrapbook, 1861 (Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1865-1877 (Item 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1868 (Item 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1869 (Item 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1881 (Item 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1883 (Item 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1883 (Item 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1883 (Item 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1883 (Item 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1890 (Item 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1892 (Item 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1894 (Item 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1915 (Item 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1916 (Item 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1916 (Item 15)
  - Scrapbook, 1916 (Item 16)
  - Scrapbook, 1946 (Item 17)
  - Album, Battalion Photo Portraits, 1881 (Item 18)
  - Album, Battalion Photo Portraits, Undated (Item 19)
  - Album, Battalion Photo Portraits, Undated (Item 20)
  - Album, Battalion Photo Portraits, Undated (Item 21)
  - Company Orders: Battery D, 1868 (Item 22)
  - Company Orders: Company F, 1873 (Item 23)
  - Company Orders: Company F, 1873 (Item 24)
  - Company Orders: Company F, 1888 (Item 25)
  - Company Orders: Company F, no entries, 1878 (Item 26)
  - Company Orders: Company F, 1878 (Item 27)
  - Company Orders: Company F, 1903-1926 (Item 28)
  - Guards Constitution, 1873 (Item 29)
  - Guards Constitution, 1878 (Item 30)
  - Guards Constitution, 1880 (Item 31)
  - Guards Constitution, 1892 (Item 32)
  - Guards Constitution, 1902 (Item 33)
  - Guards Meeting, Minutes, 1860 (Item 34)
  - Guards Meeting, Minutes, 1869 (Item 35)
  - Guards Meeting, Minutes, 1873 (Item 36)
  - Guards Meeting, Minutes, 1878 (Item 37)
  - Guards Meeting, Minutes, 1883 (Item 38)
  - Guards Meeting, Minutes, 1890 (Item 39)
  - Guards Meeting, Minutes, 1895 (Item 40)
  - Records, Company C Muster, 1873 (Item 41)
  - Ledger, Company F Quartermaster, 1868 (Item 42)
  - Ledger, Company F Quartermaster, 1903 (Item 43)
  - Ledger, Company F Quartermaster Property, 1916 (Item 44)
  - Ledger, Property Book, 1868 (Item 45)
  - Ledger, Receipts, 1868 (Item 46)
  - Ledger, Receipts, 1878 (Item 47)
  - Ledger, Battalion D Descriptive Roll, 1861 (Item 48)
  - Ledger, Cash, 1874 (Item 49)
  - Ledger, Cash, 1883 (Item 50)
  - Roll Book, Company D, 1865 (Item 51)
  - Roll Book, Company D, 1868 (Item 52)
  - Roll Book, Company D, 1872 (Item 53)
  - Roll Book, Company F, 1873 (Item 54)
  - Roll Book, Company F, 1887 (Item 55)
  - Roll Book, Company F, 1890 (Item 56)
  - Roll Book, Company F, 1900 (Item 57)
  - Rule Book, Company A, 1862 (Item 58)
  - Sick Book, Company F, 1885 (Item 59)
  - Sick Book, Company F, 1898 (Item 60)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1860-1869 (Item 61)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1874 (Item 62)
  - Record Book, Company F, no entries, 1878 (Item 63)
  - Record Book, Company F, no entries, 1878 (Item 64)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1880 (Item 65)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1886 (Item 66)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1895 (Item 67)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1903 (Item 68)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1913 (Item 69)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1867 (Item 70)
  - Record Book, Company F, 1897 (Item 71)
  - Reports, Company F, Morning, 1885 (Item 72)
  - Reports, Company F, Morning, 1890 (Item 73)
  - Reports, Company F, Morning, 1892 (Item 74)
  - Reports, Target Practice, 1878 (Item 75)
  - Reports, Target Practice, 1888 (Item 76)
  - Military Tournament, 1910 (Item 77)
  - Company History, Various (Item 78)
  - Book of the National Guardsmen, Vol. 1, 1877 (Item 79)
  - Record of Pictures and Trophies, 1884 (Item 80)
- Documents, Photographs and Artifact
  - Correspondence, 1884-1917 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1878-1927 (Box 2)
  - Rolled photographs, 1914-1918; Includes a number of photos of the Border Campaign into Mexico. (Box 3)
  - Veteran City Guards metal storage box (Box 4)